Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Pasternak, Morris and Florence: Audio Recording, 1973 March 16 (Cassette 28 & 29)
    This interview was conducted on March 16, 1973 at the home of Morris and Florence Pasternak in Queens, New York by two unidentified interviewers. The majority of the interview features Morris Pasternak’s interest in the history of the labor movement in the United States (US) and the Socialist Party of America, with interjections from his wife, Florence. He also discusses his early life in Ukraine, Russia; his education; and his working life in the US.
    Pasternak recounts his early life in a shtetl in Ukraine, including one of his older brothers mounting a defense in advance of a pogrom. He describes his development as a Socialist, including observing working conditions in the factories in which his brothers worked in Manhattan, New York; reading anarchist literature they brought home; and attending speeches by Emma Goldman with one of his brothers. Other topics include forced prostitution of Jewish immigrant women in New York City and Jewish organized crime.
    Socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Pasternak, Morris and Florence Pasternak: Transcript, 1973 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Politics, Undated (Box 16, Cassette 237)
    Sam Goldman and Dora Shapiro were siblings born in Gorlice in Polish Galicia. They had one brother and two sisters. Their father managed an oil refinery where the family lived until it closed. Their mother managed a candy store owned by the family. Goldman immigrated to the United States in 1913, and Shapiro and the rest of the family immigrated in 1921. Shapiro worked in the garment industry and was a member of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union. She met her first husband during a vacation to Cuba and they married in 1929. They divorced a few years later and she married a second time.
    Several other interviewees contribute to this compilation.
    This recording contains excerpts of several interviews, all of which focus on discussions of politics in New York, New York. These excerpts cover the conflict between local landlords and city and state legislation regarding New York building codes; an unspecified church’s view of and relationship with politics; the development and purpose of the American Labor Party; differences between the Democratic and Republican parties; and the relationship among different radical political groups in New York City. The narrators reflect on the policies and effectiveness of political figures -- including Fiorello La Guardia, Vito Marcantonio, James J. Walker, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Marcus Garvey -- and the differences between politicians at the time of the interviews and in the past.
    See also: Magliacano, Joseph; Goldman, Sam and Dora Shapiro; Sutton, Kathleen; Torres, Tony; Unger, Margareta.
  - Prescant, Becky, 1973 March 26 (Cassette Missing)
  - Preuhs, Albert, 1974 April 23 (Cassette 251, Box 25)
    Albert Preuhs was born in Hamburg, Germany on September 3, 1886. His father worked as a baker, eventually owning his own bakery. His mother worked in a kitchen for the city of Hamburg during an unspecified war but otherwise did not work outside the home. He attended school in Germany for eight years before moving into the workforce as a baker when he was 18 years old, joining a bakers’ union in Hamburg. Preuhs served in the German merchant marine and the German Navy before he immigrated to the United States (US) in January 1911. He lived in the Beggars’ Boarding House on 5th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenue in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York before getting his own apartment. He worked as a baker and joined an unspecified bakers’ union in New York (likely the Journeymen Bakers Union of New York).
    This interview was conducted by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York on April 23, 1974. This interview covers Albert Preuhs’ childhood and early adult life in Germany; his immigration to the United States (US); and a summary of his life in New York, New York. Preuhs begins by describing his father’s work in a bakery in Hamburg, Germany, noting his membership in a local union and his progression from employee to manager of his own business. He describes working as an apprentice for three years before traveling to various German cities during his time as a journeyman. Preuhs explains that he joined the German merchant marine in order to travel and was subsequently drafted into the German Navy in 1906, serving on a warship stationed in Hamburg. Upon his discharge from the Navy, he acquired a position on a merchant ship and illegally jumped ship in Hoboken, New Jersey in 1911. He describes settling in the Beggars’ Boarding House on 5th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenue in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, noting the ease with which he found work due to the myriad of small German bakeries in the city. He explains that he worked in many of these bakeries in different parts of the city and moved often in order to live near or in his current workplace. Other topics from his life in the US include the seasonal nature of the baking industry; his time working in Chicago, Illinois; and the development of technology in the baking industry and its role in the obsolescence of many physical laborers.
  - Quartaroni, Tina, Undated (Cassette 149, Box 21)
    Tina Quartaroni was born in Italy and was one of seven children. Her father was a merchant and her mother died when Quartaroni was young. She was the first of her family to immigrate to the United States when she was 21 years old and settled on Mace Avenue in the Bronx, New York. She had a variety of jobs, including dressmaking, packaging Christmas tree lights, and washing and folding laundry.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. Tina Quartaroni is hard to understand due to her heavy accent and distance from the microphone. This interview covers Quartaroni’s life in the United States (US) and the many jobs she held in the Bronx, New York. She describes her first few occupations briefly, noting that she transitioned from dressmaking to packaging Christmas tree lights before she found stable work in a laundry. She recounts joining an unspecified laundry workers’ union but notes that they didn’t strike, and conditions improved after the business was sold. She also describes her husband, including the fact that he rarely worked; his dependence on her income and pension; and their separation when she tired of his idleness and gambling.
    Quartaroni emphasizes the differences between American and Italian Catholic churches, noting that Italian churches tended to be elaborately decorated; that the Italian church fostered a tightly-knit community; and that few people regularly attended Mass in the US.
    Laundry workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Rabinowitz, Hersh, Undated (Box 29)
    Hersh Rabinowitz was born in Ukraine, Russia. He attended a polytechnic institute there for one year before World War I and the Russian Revolution. In 1920 he immigrated to Palestine, where he worked as a metal worker and served as the secretary of an unspecified metal workers' union. He was elected executive secretary of the city council of Tel Aviv and Jaffa in 1921. He and his wife immigrated to the United States in 1923 and settled in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He received his Bachelor of Science degree in physics and Master of Engineering degree from the City College of New York. He was a member of the Workmen’s Circle, Laundry Workers’ International Union Local 280, and a founding member of the Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians.
    The interviewer, date, and location are unknown. The interview covers Hersh Rabinowitz’s life in Palestine and the United States (US), including his work, political activity, and union activity. The beginning of the interview can be found in the recording titled Unidentified Russian man, Rose Gelberg, and Hersh Rabinowitz.
    Rabinowitz recounts being elected executive secretary of city council in Tel Aviv and Jaffa, Palestine in 1921; deciding to leave Palestine; and immigrating to the US in order to continue his education in 1923. He discusses studying English in order to attend night school at the City College of New York and working different jobs while attending college, including laundry worker and engineer. He discusses his union activity, explaining that he was always very active in trade unions, from his time in Palestine in a metal workers' union, as a member of the Laundry Workers’ International Union Local 280, and as a founding member of the Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians (FAECT) in 1933. He describes the collapse of FAECT in 1951, attributing it to a strike of engineers at the Electric Bond and Share Company (EBASCO) in 1947 and an investigation of FAECT by the House Un-American Activities Committee.
    Rabinowitz discusses the Socialist movement in the US, describing Socialist leaders Morris Hillquit, Meyer London, Norman Thomas, and Eugene V. Debs as giants and explaining that there was no one to succeed them. He discusses, in great detail, reasons for the failure of the Socialist movement, including leaders of powerful labor unions, such as the United Mine Workers and United Auto Workers, suggesting their members invest in the stock market and not participate in political movements as long as their financial interests were met by their employers. He provides reasons that children of immigrants would not make the same sacrifices as their parents and participate in progressive movements.
    Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians.; Engineers |x Labor Unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Palestine |x Emigration and immigration |y 20th century.
  - Rabinowitz, Hersh: Index, Undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Raia, Anthony: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 179 & 179A)
    Anthony Raia was born in Lercara Friddi, in the Palermo region of Sicily, Italy in 1904. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1920, where he worked in multiple industries. He married and had three children. Raia was a member of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union and an unspecified millinery union.
    This interview was conducted at Anthony Raia’s home in Brooklyn, New York. The interviewer and date are unknown. Throughout the interview, Raia speaks in both Italian and English. Topics of discussion include Raia’s family, his emigration from Sicily, Italy, his relationship with his wife and children, his work in the United States (US), and his union involvement. Raia discusses his immigration to the US, including his grandparents immigrating prior to his immigration; sending for his siblings to join him after the death of their father in 1920; and leaving Sicily for economic and social reasons. He recalls meeting his wife after one of her singing performances; having three children with her; feeling proud of his children's accomplishments; believing that men and women need to be treated as equals; and training his wife as a machine operator in a dress factory. He recalls different jobs he held, including work at a piano factory; on submarines in the Brooklyn Navy Yard; for the American Can Company; in shoe manufacturing; and as a part-time actor. He discusses his union involvement, including being a member of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union and an unspecified millinery union; serving on the executive board of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union; being involved in multiple strikes; and being called a Communist because of his involvement with unions.
    Hat trade |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Millinery workers |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Raia, Anthony: Interview Fact Sheet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Reid, Edward, 1975 December 12 and 18 (Box 14, Cassette 213, 213A & 213B, Box 18)
    Edward Reid was born near Montego Bay, Jamaica on April 22, 1892. He had one older brother. His father worked as a shipwright, traveling aboard ships and performing repairs as necessary, and his mother worked in a laundry. He attended Mt. Zion School in Jamaica until he was 14 years old, when he trained in carpentry. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1919 and lived with his cousin in Charleston, South Carolina for two years before migrating to New York, New York. He worked as a carpenter for a number of employers, including the Standard Oil Company and the Consolidated Gas Company in Charleston. He joined Local 52 of an unspecified union of black carpenters; the Odd Fellows; and the Freemasons while in the US.
    This interview was conducted by Jay Facciolo on December 12 and December 18, 1975 at an unknown location. This interview covers Edward Reid’s childhood in Jamaica; his immigration to the United States (US); and work as a carpenter in Charleston, South Carolina and New York, New York. Reid begins by describing his childhood in Jamaica, noting that his grandfather owned a blacksmithery and a farm that was relatively self-sufficient, growing produce and raising livestock for the family. Reid describes his time at Mt. Zion School, noting his position as a teacher’s aide once he reached the upper levels of elementary school and the fact that his mother wanted him to become a teacher, an occupation he had little interest in pursuing. He discusses the history and genealogy of parts of his family and race relations in Jamaica. He explains that when he was 16 years old, he became an apprentice to carpenters employed by his cousin, noting that he learned general carpentry and built houses and factories in Jamaica. Reid explains that he immigrated to the US in 1919 and acclimated to the United States in Charleston, South Carolina with a different cousin because of the warm weather there. He describes encountering segregation in the southern United States, noting that he ignored these restrictions with few repercussions. He describes working for the Standard Oil Company and recalls the racial segregation of the workforce. He recounts joining Local 52 of an unspecified carpenters’ union in Charleston; its two locals organized by race; and the specific territories marked for where each local’s members were allowed to work. Reid provides an extended description of his job with the Consolidated Gas Company in Charleston, noting the details of his work and his relationship with the foreman. He discusses his work at an unspecified company in New York owned by Philip Egensky. Other topics include his involvement with a church in Jamaica; his leisure activities; a comparison between race relations in the northern and southern United States; and his participation in cricket leagues in both Jamaica and the US.
    Carpenters |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Remier, [Unknown]: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 32-33)
    Mr. Remier was born in Georgia in the late 1880s. He attended Georgia State College in Savannah, Georgia. He migrated to New York, New York in 1918 with his wife and two children. They lived in the Harlem and Washington Heights neighborhoods of Manhattan before buying a house in the Bronx. He worked as a shipping clerk for the Savannah Morning News and for a French-American magazine in New York City before becoming an elevator operator. He and his wife had a third child while living in New York.
    The interviewer, location, and date of this interview and the first name of the narrator are unknown. The interviews covers Mr. Remier’s migration from Georgia to New York, New York; his social life; his experience of racial discrimination in New York; and his working life. Remier describes social activities in which he and wife participated in New York City, including a social and benevolent organization named the Georgia Association. He recounts the ease with which he and his family settled in New York, due in part to his wife having family there. He describes racial discrimination as not affecting him, as he worked and socialized exclusively within his community.
    Elevator operators |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Remier, [Unknown]: Transcript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Richards, Evadni: Audio Recording, 1973 March 28 (Box 18, Cassette 218)
    This interview was conducted by Rona Weiss on March 28, 1973 at the headquarters of the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union (ILGWU) Local 22 in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Evadni Richards’ early life in Jamaica, her immigration to the United States (US), her work in the garment industry, and her union activity. Richards discusses her early life in Jamaica, including her education at a dressmaking school in Kingston and her decision to immigrate to Cuba with a friend. She discusses working as a domestic worker and companion in Cuba before immigrating to the US in 1922. She discusses her brother’s business as a shoemaker in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and his illness, which led to his return to Jamaica in 1924 and left her alone in the US. She discusses her work in the garment industry, including her wages; her work in the designing room doing handwork; and the other West Indians who worked in the factory with her. She compares Jamaica and New York from her childhood and the 1920s, in particular that there was no segregation in schools or churches; the influence of colonialism in the workplace; and that wages were better in New York, despite still being relatively little. She discusses discrimination in the garment industry; her opinion that all workers, regardless of race or ethnicity, faced a certain amount of discrimination; and racial discrimination she faced in the garment industry, in particular not being allowed to work as a designer despite her training. She recounts being chosen to learn to operate a special sewing machine despite being the only black worker in the factory.
    Richards discusses early organizing attempts of the ILGWU in the early 1930s; her participation in strikes before she was a member of the union; and the differences in pay and working conditions after she joined the union. She discusses cultural programs organized by the ILGWU, in particular Fannia Cohn and her Know Your City program; an orchestra and dance troupe organized by the union; the popularity of these programs with the general public; her participation in the chorus; and the participation of the chorus and orchestra in the 1939-1940 New York World’s Fair. She discusses the union’s abandonment of funding of these programs in 1946 in favor of their cooperative housing programs.
    Other topics include Richards’ attendance at a singing school in the Bronx and her membership in an opera troupe; the immigration of her siblings to various countries; her decision to not become a US citizen until after her husband’s death in 1966; her childhood in the interior of Jamaica; and her relationships with her extended family.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York,New York and the United States; Life Before Immigration or Migration; Leisure; and Nieghborhood.
  - Richards, Evandi: Index, 1973 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Reif, Fannie, 1973 April 2 (Cassette 34)
    Fannie Rief was born in 1890 in a small town in southern Austria. Her father was a glazier and a cantor. Rief immigrated to the United States in 1907, where she married and had one son.
    This interview was conducted by Manfred Putzka on April 2, 1973 at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York. The interview covers Fannie Rief’s childhood in Austria, her immigration to the United States (US), her working life, and her family life. Rief recounts aspects of her early life in Austria, including brief biographies of her siblings. She recounts not attending school as only boys were formally educated and teaching herself to read and write Yiddish. She discusses anti-Semitism, wondering why it exists, and her belief that Jews were treated better in Austria than in Germany and Russia. She recounts immigrating alone to the US in 1907 and living with a family friend in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She describes working as a servant for a number of Jewish families in New York City. She discusses her belief that although life in the US was hard, it was better than her life in Europe and describes ways in which new immigrants helped each other acclimate to life in the US. She discusses the decline in religious adherence in US amongst Jewish immigrants. She recalls her husband’s career as a machine operator in a ladieswear shop and his activity in an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union). She discusses her son’s education, his marriage, and his worry over her health and well-being.
  - Reif, Fanny: Transcript, 1973 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Robinson, Irene: Audio Recording, 1973 (Cassette 219)
    This interview was conducted by Edmund Lake and Scott Holmes in 1973 at Irene Robinson’s home at 220 Kingston Avenue in Brooklyn, New York. The date is unknown. This interview covers Robinson’s childhood in British Guiana; her immigration to the United States (US) in 1924; and her life and work in New York, New York. Robinson begins by describing her childhood in Plaisance, British Guiana, recalling how discipline and the desire to make something of herself were instilled in her through her household chores, education, and corporal punishment. She describes the racial demographics of her classmates as being mostly black but not feeling animosity between the black and East Indian populations of British Guiana; and not experiencing racial discrimination and prejudice until she lived in the US. She discusses Great Britain’s relationship with British Guiana and her work as secretary in a Marcus Garvey club in British Guiana.
    Robinson recalls wanting to come to the US because she had heard that American stenographers earned good wages. She describes her journey to the US in March 1924, during which she felt seasick and alone, and nearly died when her ship sank. She recalls living with her friend’s sister on 128th Street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and her awe at seeing snow for the first time. She recounts a trip she and her husband took to the southern US after they were married, focusing on her initial experience with racial discrimination in the US and how it made her wary of people. She describes moving near Linden Boulevard in Brooklyn in order to provide a safer environment and better educational opportunities for her children.
    Robinson explains that she went into factory work because the hours allowed her to care for her children and that one of her friends taught her to operate a sewing machine. She recalls working for various garment factories and joining Local 140 of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union), which supported members financially during strikes and helped them achieve better working conditions and wages. She emphasizes the role of the Anglican Church throughout her life and her children’s experiences at Greater Refuge Temple in Harlem. Other topics include the life, education, and work of her five children; her and cousins’ appearances as a singing group, the Robinson Children, on various New York City radio stations; her husband’s occupations; a comparison of parenting methodologies between her generation and the generation of parents at the time of the interview; and her travels since her retirement in 1967.